<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Applications on OpenMS</title><link>https://openms.de/application/</link><description>Recent content in Applications on OpenMS</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://openms.de/application/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Data-independent acquisition metabolomics analyzer (DIAMETALYZER)</title><link>https://openms.de/application/diametalyzer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.de/application/diametalyzer/</guid><description>DIAMetAlyzer is a KNIME workflow which integrates DDA and targeted DIA analysis for metabolomics, which allows for false-discovery rate estimation based a target-decoy approach (see figure 1). It performs DDA based candidate identification and constructs a target/decoy assay library, which is used for DIA target extraction and statistical validation (FDR estimation)
Fig. 1: DIAMetAlyzer – pipeline for assay library generation and targeted analysis with statistical validation
Candidate identification includes feature detection, adduct grouping and accurate mass search.</description></item><item><title>Efficient bayesian protein inference (EPIFANY)</title><link>https://openms.de/application/epifany/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.de/application/epifany/</guid><description>Introduction EPIFANY is a protein inference engine based on a Bayesian network. Currently, a similar model to Fido is used with the main parameters alpha (pep_emission), beta (pep_spurious_emission) and gamma (prot_prior). If not specified, these parameters are trained based on their classification performance and calibration via a grid search by simply running with several possible combinations and evaluating. Unless you see very extreme output probabilities (e.g. many close to 1.</description></item><item><title>Nucleic acid search engine (NASE)</title><link>https://openms.de/application/nase/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.de/application/nase/</guid><description>NASE is now included in OpenMS release, 2.5.
Requirements:
HCD (or ETD) data of RNA oligonucleotides acquired on a high-resolution mass spectrometer Fragment spectra (MS/MS) need to be centroided (either on acquisition, conversion, or in a workflow using the TOPP tool PeakPickerHiRes) Developed and tested on Linux (Ubuntu 18.04 and 18.10) systems with data from orbitrap instruments Operating system: OpenMS installers have been tested on Ubuntu Linux 18.04, Windows 7/8/10, and macOS 10.</description></item><item><title>Protein-protein cross-linking (OPENPEPXL)</title><link>https://openms.de/application/openpepxl/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.de/application/openpepxl/</guid><description>OpenPepXL: an open source peptide cross-link identification tool OpenPepXL is a protein-protein cross-link identification tool implemented in C++ as part of OpenMS. It works with all uncleavable labeled and label-free cross-linkers but not (yet) with cleavable ones.
Requirements The current version of OpenPepXL, version 1.1 is available as part of OpenMS 2.5. Installers for Windows, MacOS and Linux can be found here. OpenPepXL can be used effectively on a desktop computer with 16BG of memory.</description></item><item><title>Quantification and identification of mhc peptides (MHCQUANT)</title><link>https://openms.de/application/mhcquant/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.de/application/mhcquant/</guid><description>MHCquant: Identify and quantify peptides from mass spectrometry raw data
MHCquant is an analysis pipeline used for quantitative processing of data dependent (DDA) peptidomics data.
It was specifically designed to analyze immunopeptidomics data, which deals with the analysis of affinity-purified, unspecifically cleaved peptides that have recently been discussed intensively in the context of cancer vaccines. (https://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms13404)
The workflow is based on the OpenMS C++ framework for computational mass spectrometry.</description></item><item><title>Quantitative data independent proteomics (DIAPROTEOMICS)</title><link>https://openms.de/application/diaproteomics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.de/application/diaproteomics/</guid><description>DIAproteomics is a bioinformatics analysis pipeline used for quantitative processing of data independent (DIA) proteomics data.
The workflow is based on the OpenSwathWorkflow for SWATH-MS proteomic data. DIA RAW files (mzML) serve as inputs and library search is performed based on a given input spectral library. If specified internal retention time standards (irts) will be used to align library and DIA measurements into the same retention time space. FDR rescoring is applied using Pyprophet based on a competitive target-decoy approach on peakgroup or global peptide and protein level.</description></item><item><title>RNA-PROTIEN CROSS-LINKING (RNPXL)</title><link>https://openms.de/application/rnpxl/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.de/application/rnpxl/</guid><description>RNPxl has been integrated into OpenMS and also the Proteome Discoverer Community Nodes. No custom installer is required anymore. RNPxl has been integrated into OpenMS and also the Proteome Discoverer Community Nodes. No custom installer is required anymore.
Requirements: HCD data acquired on a high-resolution MS Developed and tested on orbitrap instruments MS and MS/MS need to be centroided (either on acquisition, conversion or in a workflow using the TOPP tool HiResPeakPicker) For additional information on sample handling and acquisition, as well as a detailed step-by-step tutorial, please refer to the supplementary material of the publication.</description></item><item><title>STABLE ISOTOPE PROBING (METAPROSIP)</title><link>https://openms.de/application/metaprosip/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.de/application/metaprosip/</guid><description>MetaProSIP: automated inference of elemental fluxes in microbial communities &amp;nbsp;Info MetaProSIP has been fully integrated into OpenMS. No additional installer is required anymore. Update: MetaProSIP now supports labeling experiments with heavy water (D, 18O)
Download an updated KNIME workflow: here
Advanced workflow including mass recalibration, alignment, and ID pooling: here
Requirements High-Resolution MS, CID, or HCD MS2 Developed and tested on orbitrap instruments MS1 and MS2 need to be centroided (either on acquisition, conversion or in a workflow using the TOPP tool HiResPeakPicker) For additional information on sample handling and acquisition please refer to the original MetaProSIP publication.</description></item><item><title>ULTRA-FAST MS1/MS2 DECONVOLUTION FOR TOP-DOWN PROTEOMICS</title><link>https://openms.de/application/flashdeconv/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.de/application/flashdeconv/</guid><description>FLASHDECONV 2.0 BETA+, FINALLY WITH A GUI! Finally a GUI is here. You can find the GUI command in [OpenMS path]/bin folder. Go to [OpenMS path]/bin and run FLASHDeconvWizard! FLASHDeconv 2.0 beta+ works for MS1 and MS2 spectral deconvolution and feature deconvolution. It supports various output formats (e.g., *.tsv, *.mzML, *.msalign, and *.feature). FLASHDeconv 2.0 stable version will be officially integrated in OpenMS 2.7.0 released in near future. FLASHDeconv 2.0 beta+ also supports TopPIC identification better than the previous version, by generating all msalign and feature files for TopPIC inputs.</description></item></channel></rss>