<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Keyfeatures on openms</title><link>https://openms.org/keyfeatures/</link><description>Recent content in Keyfeatures on openms</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://openms.org/keyfeatures/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>OpenMS For Metabolomics</title><link>https://openms.org/keyfeatures/metabolomics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/keyfeatures/metabolomics/</guid><description>OPENMS FOR METABOLOMICS Many of the tools and algorithms provided by OpenMS are developed with both proteomics and metabolomics in mind. First you convert vendor-specific formats into an open community-driven format. You can then filter, centroid, and recalibrate your spectra. OpenMS provides tools that are specifically designed for the metabolite quantification and metabolite identification. All tools are available as nodes in the workflow engine KNIME. In addition the complete workflow for the analysis of non-targeted metabolomics data is also available as a plugin for Thermo Compound Discoverer.</description></item><item><title>OpenMS For Proteomics</title><link>https://openms.org/keyfeatures/proteomics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/keyfeatures/proteomics/</guid><description>OpenMS provides a large amount of tools to analyse your proteomics datasets. Starting from input files in either vendor-specific raw formats (convertible with the integrated ProteoWizard) or a number of open HUPO-compliant formats (mzML, mzXML), you can process your data by simply combining a set of our almost 200 ready-made tools from „The OpenMS proteomics pipeline (TOPP)”. These tools are available on the command line, from within workflow engines (e.</description></item><item><title>OpenMS For Workflows</title><link>https://openms.org/keyfeatures/workflows/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/keyfeatures/workflows/</guid><description>OPENMS IN KNIME As part of the Center for Integrative Bioinformatics (CiBi) in the German Network for Bioinformatics (deNBI), we are currently focusing our development efforts on the integration of OpenMS into KNIME. KNIME is a well-established data analysis framework that supports the generation of workflows for data analysis. Using a Common Tool Description (CTD) file which is writeable by every TOPP tool and a node generator program (Generic Knime Nodes), all TOPP tools can be made available to run in KNIME.</description></item></channel></rss>