<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>openms</title><link>https://openms.org/</link><description>Recent content on openms</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://openms.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>404</title><link>https://openms.org/404/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/404/</guid><description>Oops! You&amp;rsquo;ve reached a dead end.
If you think something should be here, you can open an issue on GitHub.</description></item><item><title>About Us</title><link>https://openms.org/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/about/</guid><description>Some information about the OpenMS project and community
OpenMS is an open-source software C++ library for LC-MS data management and analyses. It offers an infrastructure for rapid development of mass spectrometry related software. OpenMS is free software available under the three clause BSD license and runs under Windows, macOS, and Linux. OpenMS will always be 100% open source software, free for all to use and released under the liberal terms of the modified BSD license.</description></item><item><title>Applications</title><link>https://openms.org/applications/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/applications/</guid><description>OpenMS is a flexible codebase that can be tailored to many different applications ranging from the standard label free analysis to top down, metabolomics, crosslinking or DIA.
Choose an application of OpenMS that you are interested in. The pages will provide explanations on how OpenMS can be used to solve your problems and link to workflows that allow you to apply the tools to your data.
If you cannot find your application in the menu on the left, more OpenMS tools can be found in the TOPP documentation.</description></item><item><title>Array Computing</title><link>https://openms.org/arraycomputing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/arraycomputing/</guid><description>Array computing is the foundation of statistical, mathematical, scientific computing in various contemporary data science and analytics applications such as data visualization, digital signal processing, image processing, bioinformatics, machine learning, AI, and several others.
Large scale data manipulation and transformation depends on efficient, high-performance array computing. The language of choice for data analytics, machine learning, and productive numerical computing is Python.
Numerical Python or openms is its de-facto standard Python programming language library that supports large, multi-dimensional arrays and matrices, and comes with a vast collection of high-level mathematical functions to operate on these arrays.</description></item><item><title>Citing OpenMS</title><link>https://openms.org/citing-openms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/citing-openms/</guid><description>Röst, H.L., Sachsenberg, T., Aiche, S., Bielow, C., Weisser, H., Aicheler, F., Andreotti, S., Ehrlich, H.-C., Gutenbrunner, P., Kenar, E., Liang, X., Nahnsen, S., Nilse, L., Pfeuffer, J., Rosenberger, G., Rurik, M., Schmitt, U., Veit, J., Walzer, M., Wojnar, D., Wolski, W.E., Schilling, O., Choudhary, J.S., Malmström, L., Aebersold, R., Reinert, K., Kohlbacher, O.
OpenMS: A flexible open-source software platform for mass spectrometry data analysis. Nature Methods, vol. 13, 2016.</description></item><item><title>Community</title><link>https://openms.org/community/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/community/</guid><description>openms is a community-driven open source project developed by a diverse group of contributors. The openms leadership has made a strong commitment to creating an open, inclusive, and positive community. Please read the openms Code of Conduct for guidance on how to interact with others in a way that makes the community thrive.
We offer several communication channels to learn, share your knowledge and connect with others within the openms community.</description></item><item><title>Contribute to openms</title><link>https://openms.org/contribute/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/contribute/</guid><description>The openMS project welcomes your expertise and enthusiasm! Your choices aren&amp;rsquo;t limited to programming, as you can see below there are many areas where we need your help.
If you&amp;rsquo;re unsure where to start or how your skills fit in, reach out! You can ask on the mailing list or GitHub (open an issue or comment on a relevant issue).
Those are our preferred channels (open source is open by nature), but if you prefer to talk privately, contact our community coordinators at mailing list or on Gitter.</description></item><item><title>DATA-INDEPENDENT ACQUISITION METABOLOMICS ANALYZER (DIAMETALYZER)</title><link>https://openms.org/application/diametalyzer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/application/diametalyzer/</guid><description>DIAMetAlyzer is a KNIME workflow which integrates DDA and targeted DIA analysis for metabolomics, which allows for false-discovery rate estimation based a target-decoy approach (see figure 1). It performs DDA based candidate identification and constructs a target/decoy assay library, which is used for DIA target extraction and statistical validation (FDR estimation)
Fig. 1: DIAMetAlyzer – pipeline for assay library generation and targeted analysis with statistical validation
Candidate identification includes feature detection, adduct grouping and accurate mass search.</description></item><item><title>Develop Your Own Openms Tools</title><link>https://openms.org/getting-started/develop-your-own-openms-tools/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/getting-started/develop-your-own-openms-tools/</guid><description>SOURCE CODE The source code of the OpenMS library as well as the TOPP tools and TOPPView are hosted on GitHub. The most important repositories for starting developers will be OpenMS itself and its contrib (i.e. its dependencies). The source code is released under a three-clause BSD license.
DOCUMENTATION A good starting point for developers is the OpenMS GitHub wiki. For a quick dive into developing your own, see the Developer FAQ and the Adding your own tool to the TOPP suite.</description></item><item><title>Example Workflows</title><link>https://openms.org/knime-example-workflows/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/knime-example-workflows/</guid><description>On this page we list some KNIME and TOPPAS workflows which we find useful and worth sharing. Most of them are tested and were successfully used in projects. If you run into trouble executing one of these workflows, please file an issue.
KNIME WORKFLOWS We are currently building a workflow repository for KNIME so stay tuned. Below you find some workflows we assembled for previous user meetings.
In KNIME, you can import ready-made workflows.</description></item><item><title>Get Help</title><link>https://openms.org/gethelp/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/gethelp/</guid><description>User questions: The best way to get help is to post your question to a site like StackOverflow, with thousands of users available to answer. Smaller alternatives include Gitter. We wish we could keep an eye on these sites, or answer questions directly, but the volume is just a little overwhelming!
Development issues: For openms development-related matters (e.g. bug reports), please see Community.
StackOverflow A forum for asking usage questions, e.</description></item><item><title>Help Request</title><link>https://openms.org/help-request/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/help-request/</guid><description>Loading…</description></item><item><title>History of openms</title><link>https://openms.org/history/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/history/</guid><description>openms is a foundational Python library that provides array data structures and related fast numerical routines. When started, the library had little funding, and was written mainly by graduate students—many of them without computer science education, and often without a blessing of their advisors. To even imagine that a small group of “rogue” student programmers could upend the already well-established ecosystem of research software—backed by millions in funding and many hundreds of highly qualified engineers — was preposterous.</description></item><item><title>Installing openms</title><link>https://openms.org/install/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/install/</guid><description>Installation instructions: Here you can select the operating system of your choce and follow the installation instructions.
Installation on GNU/Linux Install Debian package If you are using a Debian-based Linux we suggest to use the deb-package provided by us in our archive. It is most easily installed with &amp;ldquo;gdebi&amp;rdquo; which automatically resolves the dependencies if they are available in your repositories.
sudo apt-get install gdebi sudo gdebi /PATH/TO/OpenMS.deb To ensure the tool functionality please add the OPENMS_DATA_PATH variable to your environment as follows (you will get an error advising you this when executing a tool):</description></item><item><title>News</title><link>https://openms.org/news/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/news/</guid><description>SECOND OPENMS DOCUMENTATION UPDATE The OpenMS team has won a 2022 Google Season of Docs grant to update the OpenMS documentation. Combined with money from the University of Tübingen, a team of three technical writers will review and rewrite OpenMS documentation. The 2022 team consists of Rahul Agrawal, Christina Kumar and Tapasweni Pathak.
OPENMS DEVELOPERS’ MEETING 4-8 APRIL 2022 Dec 31, 2021 &amp;ndash; The OpenMS developer meeting brings bioinformaticians working in computational mass spectrometry together to shape the future development of OpenMS.</description></item><item><title>openms Code of Conduct</title><link>https://openms.org/code-of-conduct/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/code-of-conduct/</guid><description>Introduction This Code of Conduct applies to all spaces managed by the openms project, including all public and private mailing lists, issue trackers, wikis, blogs, Twitter, and any other communication channel used by our community. The openms project does not organise in-person events, however events related to our community should have a code of conduct similar in spirit to this one.
This Code of Conduct should be honored by everyone who participates in the openms community formally or informally, or claims any affiliation with the project, in any project-related activities and especially when representing the project, in any role.</description></item><item><title>openms Code of Conduct - How to follow up on a report</title><link>https://openms.org/report-handling-manual/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/report-handling-manual/</guid><description>This is the manual followed by openms’s Code of Conduct Committee. It’s used when we respond to an issue to make sure we’re consistent and fair.
Enforcing the Code of Conduct impacts our community today and for the future. It’s an action that we do not take lightly. When reviewing enforcement measures, the Code of Conduct Committee will keep the following values and guidelines in mind:
Act in a personal manner rather than impersonal.</description></item><item><title>openms Diversity and Inclusion Statement</title><link>https://openms.org/diversity_sep2020/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/diversity_sep2020/</guid><description>In light of the foregoing discussion on social media after publication of the openms paper in Nature and the concerns raised about the state of diversity and inclusion on the openms team, we would like to issue the following statement:
It is our strong belief that we are at our best, as a team and community, when we are inclusive and equitable. Being an international team from the onset, we recognize the value of collaborating with individuals from diverse backgrounds and expertise.</description></item><item><title>OpenMS For Metabolomics</title><link>https://openms.org/keyfeatures/metabolomics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/keyfeatures/metabolomics/</guid><description>OPENMS FOR METABOLOMICS Many of the tools and algorithms provided by OpenMS are developed with both proteomics and metabolomics in mind. First you convert vendor-specific formats into an open community-driven format. You can then filter, centroid, and recalibrate your spectra. OpenMS provides tools that are specifically designed for the metabolite quantification and metabolite identification. All tools are available as nodes in the workflow engine KNIME. In addition the complete workflow for the analysis of non-targeted metabolomics data is also available as a plugin for Thermo Compound Discoverer.</description></item><item><title>OpenMS For Proteomics</title><link>https://openms.org/keyfeatures/proteomics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/keyfeatures/proteomics/</guid><description>OpenMS provides a large amount of tools to analyse your proteomics datasets. Starting from input files in either vendor-specific raw formats (convertible with the integrated ProteoWizard) or a number of open HUPO-compliant formats (mzML, mzXML), you can process your data by simply combining a set of our almost 200 ready-made tools from „The OpenMS proteomics pipeline (TOPP)”. These tools are available on the command line, from within workflow engines (e.</description></item><item><title>OpenMS For Workflows</title><link>https://openms.org/keyfeatures/workflows/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/keyfeatures/workflows/</guid><description>OPENMS IN KNIME As part of the Center for Integrative Bioinformatics (CiBi) in the German Network for Bioinformatics (deNBI), we are currently focusing our development efforts on the integration of OpenMS into KNIME. KNIME is a well-established data analysis framework that supports the generation of workflows for data analysis. Using a Common Tool Description (CTD) file which is writeable by every TOPP tool and a node generator program (Generic Knime Nodes), all TOPP tools can be made available to run in KNIME.</description></item><item><title>openms Teams</title><link>https://openms.org/teams/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/teams/</guid><description>We are an international team on a mission to support scientific and research communities worldwide by building quality, open-source software. Join us!
Maintainers Julianus Pfeuffer Timo Sachsenberg Kyowon Jeong Axel Walter Samuel Wein Tjeerd Dijkstra Jihyung Kim Eugen Netz Matteo Pilz Ayesha Feroz Arslan Siraj Efi Kontou Chris Bielow Hendrik Weisser Hannes Roest Docs team Rahul Agrawal Christina Kumar Tapasweni Pathak Funding and grants team Oliver Kohlbacher Timo Sachsenberg Hannes Roest Tjeerd Dijkstra Governance For the list of the Steering Council members, please see here.</description></item><item><title>Press kit</title><link>https://openms.org/press-kit/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/press-kit/</guid><description>We would like to make it easy for you to include the openms project identity in your next academic paper, course materials, or presentation.
You will find several high-resolution versions of the openms logo here. Note that by using the openms.org resources, you accept the openms Code of Conduct.</description></item><item><title>Privacy Policy</title><link>https://openms.org/privacy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/privacy/</guid><description>WHO WE ARE Our website address is: http(s)://www.openms.de
WHAT PERSONAL DATA WE COLLECT AND WHY WE COLLECT IT Comments When visitors leave comments on the site we collect the data shown in the comments form, and also the visitor’s IP address and browser user agent string to help spam detection.
An anonymized string created from your email address (also called a hash) may be provided to the Gravatar service to see if you are using it.</description></item><item><title>PROTEIN-PROTEIN CROSS-LINKING (OPENPEPXL)</title><link>https://openms.org/application/openpepxl/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/application/openpepxl/</guid><description>OpenPepXL: an open source peptide cross-link identification tool OpenPepXL is a protein-protein cross-link identification tool implemented in C++ as part of OpenMS. It works with all uncleavable labeled and label-free cross-linkers but not (yet) with cleavable ones.
Requirements The current version of OpenPepXL, version 1.1 is available as part of OpenMS 2.5. Installers for Windows, MacOS and Linux can be found here. OpenPepXL can be used effectively on a desktop computer with 16BG of memory.</description></item><item><title>Publications</title><link>https://openms.org/publications/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/publications/</guid><description>2021 A. Marcu, L. Bichmann, L. Kuchenbecker, D. J. Kowalewski, L. K. Freudenmann, L. Backert, L. Mühlenbruch, A. Szolek, M. Lübke, P. Wagner, and others, “HLA Ligand Atlas: a benign reference of HLA-presented peptides to improve T-cell-based cancer immunotherapy,” Journal for immunotherapy of cancer, vol. 9, iss. 4, 2021. [Bibtex] @article{marcu2021hla, title={HLA Ligand Atlas: a benign reference of HLA-presented peptides to improve T-cell-based cancer immunotherapy}, author={Marcu, Ana and Bichmann, Leon and Kuchenbecker, Leon and Kowalewski, Daniel Johannes and Freudenmann, Lena Katharina and Backert, Linus and M{\"</description></item><item><title>QUANTIFICATION AND IDENTIFICATION OF MHC PEPTIDES (MHCQUANT)</title><link>https://openms.org/application/mhcquant/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/application/mhcquant/</guid><description>MHCquant: Identify and quantify peptides from mass spectrometry raw data
MHCquant is an analysis pipeline used for quantitative processing of data dependent (DDA) peptidomics data.
It was specifically designed to analyze immunopeptidomics data, which deals with the analysis of affinity-purified, unspecifically cleaved peptides that have recently been discussed intensively in the context of cancer vaccines. (https://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms13404)
The workflow is based on the OpenMS C++ framework for computational mass spectrometry.</description></item><item><title>QUANTITATIVE DATA INDEPENDENT PROTEOMICS (DIAPROTEOMICS)</title><link>https://openms.org/application/diaproteomics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/application/diaproteomics/</guid><description>DIAproteomics: Automated quantitative analysis of DIA proteomics mass spectrometry measurements DIAproteomics is a bioinformatics analysis pipeline used for quantitative processing of data independent (DIA) proteomics data.
The workflow is based on the OpenSwathWorkflow for SWATH-MS proteomic data. DIA RAW files (mzML) serve as inputs and library search is performed based on a given input spectral library. If specified internal retention time standards (irts) will be used to align library and DIA measurements into the same retention time space.</description></item><item><title>RNA-PROTEIN CROSS-LINKING (RNPXL)</title><link>https://openms.org/application/rnpxl/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/application/rnpxl/</guid><description>RNPxl has been integrated into OpenMS and also the Proteome Discoverer Community Nodes. No custom installer is required anymore. RNPxl has been integrated into OpenMS and also the Proteome Discoverer Community Nodes. No custom installer is required anymore.
Requirements: HCD data acquired on a high-resolution MS Developed and tested on orbitrap instruments MS and MS/MS need to be centroided (either on acquisition, conversion or in a workflow using the TOPP tool HiResPeakPicker) For additional information on sample handling and acquisition, as well as a detailed step-by-step tutorial, please refer to the supplementary material of the publication.</description></item><item><title>STABLE ISOTOPE PROBING (METAPROSIP)</title><link>https://openms.org/application/metaprosip/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/application/metaprosip/</guid><description>MetaProSIP: automated inference of elemental fluxes in microbial communities 🛈 &amp;nbsp;Info MetaProSIP has been fully integrated into OpenMS. No additional installer is required anymore. Update: MetaProSIP now supports labeling experiments with heavy water (D, 18O)
Download an updated KNIME workflow: here
Advanced workflow including mass recalibration, alignment, and ID pooling: here
Requirements High-Resolution MS, CID, or HCD MS2 Developed and tested on orbitrap instruments MS1 and MS2 need to be centroided (either on acquisition, conversion or in a workflow using the TOPP tool HiResPeakPicker) For additional information on sample handling and acquisition please refer to the original MetaProSIP publication.</description></item><item><title>Terms of Use</title><link>https://openms.org/terms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/terms/</guid><description>Last updated January 4, 2020
AGREEMENT TO TERMS These Terms of Use constitute a legally binding agreement made between you, whether personally or on behalf of an entity (“you”) and openms (&amp;quot;Project&amp;quot;, “we”, “us”, or “our”), concerning your access to and use of the openms.org website as well as any other media form, media channel, mobile website or mobile application related, linked, or otherwise connected thereto (collectively, the “Site”). You agree that by accessing the Site, you have read, understood, and agreed to be bound by all of these Terms of Use.</description></item><item><title>Training</title><link>https://openms.org/training/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/training/</guid><description> TRAINING EVENTS Upcoming and past hands-on tutorial sessions and other OpenMS training events
TUTORIALS Online resources for our core OpenMS and TOPP tutorials
ADDITIONAL MATERIALS Related materials helpful for deeper understanding of the general concepts as well as advanced literature (online lectures, related tutorials etc.)</description></item><item><title>ULTRA-FAST MS1/MS2 DECONVOLUTION FOR TOP-DOWN PROTEOMICS</title><link>https://openms.org/application/flashdeconv/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/application/flashdeconv/</guid><description>FLASHDECONV 2.0 BETA+, FINALLY WITH A GUI! Finally a GUI is here. You can find the GUI command in [OpenMS path]/bin folder. Go to [OpenMS path]/bin and run FLASHDeconvWizard! FLASHDeconv 2.0 beta+ works for MS1 and MS2 spectral deconvolution and feature deconvolution. It supports various output formats (e.g., *.tsv, *.mzML, *.msalign, and *.feature). FLASHDeconv 2.0 stable version will be officially integrated in OpenMS 2.7.0 released in near future. FLASHDeconv 2.0 beta+ also supports TopPIC identification better than the previous version, by generating all msalign and feature files for TopPIC inputs.</description></item><item><title>Use OpenMS in CD/PD</title><link>https://openms.org/getting-started/p-and-c-discoverer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openms.org/getting-started/p-and-c-discoverer/</guid><description>Overview PROTEOME AND COMPOUND DISCOVERER INTEGRATION We provide integrated workflow solutions for the Thermo Proteome Discoverer and Compound Discoverer platforms powered by OpenMS.
PROTEOME DISCOVERER Starting from version 2.0, Proteome Discoverer functionality can be extended by external plugins. Several OpenMS workflows are now made available as Proteome Discoverer Community Nodes. Installer packages and workflows can be downloaded from here.
Example workflow in KNIME
COMPOUND DISCOVERER MetaboProfiler provides functionality of multiple OpenMS 2.</description></item></channel></rss>